[ HEARTBEAT ]
NINA: Abstract image of an eye.
[ ♪ PERCUSSION AND SYNTH MUSIC STARTS ♪ ]
Am I crazy? Am I blind?
Should I be hard or should I be kind?
As I stand and shake my head,
for no one knows what I see,
yet I am always there to please.
Colours wash over the screen.
MILES: They're not real,
[ ♪ MUSIC RISES ♪ ]
or they're more real, should I say than
maybe a sighted person can imagine.
You probably do without realising,
but you can feel
when things are there,
even if you're not touching them.
You learn,
as someone who can't see at all,
to rely on that feeling.
It's, y-you know, it saves you.
And these hallucinations are so real.
Yes, you can see them
[ ♪ MUSIC CLIMAXES ♪ ]
but you also feel them.
[ ♪ MUSIC FADES OUT ♪ ]
NARRATOR: Aspectum
MILES: I’m Miles.
I'm at the empty Cricket Stadium.
[ SHOUTING AND BALL THUDDING ]
I started playing County and
then started playing International
England cricket from '98 through to 2008.
[ CLAPPING ]
It's a lot of really good fun.
It was got to see places around the world that
I wouldn't have been able to see
had I been able to see.
[ FOOTBALL THUDDING ]
through just playing cricket, the sport that I've loved
[ LAWN MOWER ]
since I was, as far back as I can remember.
With my dad, when I was 5 years old
sat on the sofa,
with him explaining fielding positions.
When I was 18-months old,
my mum noticed that the
[ CLINKING NOISE BUILDS ]
pupil in my right eye wasn't working properly
when she turned the lights on and off and
took me off down to the doctor's,
then went straight down there
and was diagnosed with Retina Blastoma.
So it's a cancer of the retina.
It's in both eyes, but it was much further
[ LOW PITCH DRONE ]
progressed in my right eye.
So far so they had to remove
that eye instantly and straight away.
They reckoned that, sort of five weeks later, the
cancer would have been into the optic nerve
and the brain, and that would have been "it".
[ RISING SINE WAVE ]
That would have been the end of stuff.
[ SHOUTING AND BALL THUDDING ]
I did radiotherapy on my left eye for the next 3 years.
Some cobalt plaques on the back of the eyeball
and all that sort of stuff to try and fry the
fry t-the cancer.
But in the end, it just, i-it didn't work.
It was too resilient.
So they took my left eye,
when I was four and a half.
[ CRACKLING NOISE BUILDS ]
NINA: I'm Nina.
I developed a sight condition when I was 2 years old.
I caught the flu virus, and it attacked my eyes.
It left me with different problems.
[ CLINKING NOISE ]
I lost my right eye 13 years ago in an accident at work
and then I lost the retina out of the left eye
coming up to 4 years ago now,
in an accident at home.
[ MUSIC TBC ]
[ KETTLE WHISTLING ]
That morning, I was taking too much on,
doing the payroll for the staff at the cafe
I was trying to get my son ready for school.
I bent over, basically caught the corner of the TV
and it burst a hole in the top of my eyeball.
And I knew straight away the sight just, it went just black.
[ ♪ EERIE ELECTRONIC MUSIC ♪ ]
There was just like lines of lightning.
And I just knew.
I knew that the sight had gone.
[ BUZZING ]
It was quite frightening.
I came around from surgery,
and I just saw waves of blue and red
[ EAR RINGING NOISE ]
and I thought
“They saved something that I can see.
I can see something, they've saved some of my sight."
Doctor came back, and I remember these words.
He said, "I can reassure you we haven't saved your sight,
it's just your mind playing tricks on you."
So, those words kind of haunted me,
because I thought,
“Well, I can see something,
there's something there for sure."
[ SINE WAVE ]
Because he said that to me,
I was really scared to tell anybody.
[ WATER FLOWING ]
Waves of blue, yellow, and green wash over the screen.
The images started to develop from that point,
and I started seeing patterns and shapes and the colours.
The blue and red turned into green
and yellow and pink and purple
and then they started forming shapes
[ ♪ EERIE ELECTRONIC MUSIC ♪ ]
and then they became faces. And the faces were
kind of turned into like a
a skull, a zombie skull.
And they had no eyes in the sockets
and they had blood dripping down the cheeks.
It just become too scary.
I was just sat there crying
kind of huddled on the sofa in the corner,
just scared of these zombies that were there.
Here's some artwork I made of the skulls.
[ ♪ PIANO NOTE ♪ ]
MILES: We enter a doll's house recreation of my childhood home.
[ ♪ EERIE MUSIC STARTS ♪ ]
So, I first started getting hallucinations
when I was probably about four.
I think it was just before I totally lost my sight.
[ CREAKING SOUND ]
Mine have always been, what I've always called "monsters",
[ WHOOSH ]
Ones that were good, ones that were friendly,
ones that weren't.
So, I guess the friendly ones,
they just sort of sat back,
[ WHOOSH ]
they were never a threat.
There were two, in particular, I remember
when I was young, and they were sort of snakes,
[ HISSES ]
and they were not friendy.
They were as thick as your arm
and they had kind of thick wormy hair.
When you're a child, your parents have gone out,
and your grandparents are sitting for the evening,
and you've gone to bed,
sometimes the child would wake up and go,
"I want me mum, I want my dad," or whatever.
[ CREAKING SOUND ]
I couldn't go to the door
to call downstairs to my gran or my granddad or whatever,
because as soon as I opened the door a crack,
[ ♪ DRUM BEATS STARTS ♪ ]
one or both of these snakes would be outside
and they'd try and come through the door
so you might whip it open shout, slam it,
and dive back into bed again.
But you probably wouldn't,
so you either just shouted
a lot from there or you bottled everything up,
and got under the duet where you couldn't see,
metaphorically speaking.
Because that works for me.
If I’m seeing a monster,
if I cover my eyes
I can't see it.
Worked that one out.
NINA: I walk through a mirror maze with my cane.
[ SOFT METAL CLANKING ]
Reflections of myself appearing and disappearing.
[ ♪ MUSIC STARTS DRUMS ♪ ]
It does have an impact, and some days I feel like
“God, I just can't carry on, I'm just this…
[ ♪ PERCUSSION ADDED ♪ ]
I can't cope with this anymore, I need to close
I need to go away, I need to get away,
I need to escape it, and I can't escape it.
It's there!”
And I have them bad days.
So, for me, I experience them all day, every day.
So from the moment I wake to the moment I get to sleep
or when I get to sleep,
because that is one thing that I struggle with, getting to sleep,
because when the hallucinations are there,
they're there when I close my eyes.
They don't go away.
It drives me insane sometimes.
I just. like… I know it sounds, and I know
I probably shouldn’t say this in front of everyone but…
[ ♪ DRUMS FADE ♪ ]
like some days, and especially it's more at night time
when I'm trying to get to sleep, but
I smack myself on the head.
I shake.
You know, I lie there in bed crying
begging for it to go away,
because I just want to go to sleep.
And that is really difficult to live with.
[ SOFT METAL CLANKING ]
And when you can't make it go away,
that's hard.
And then you feel,
then you get guilt and shame
for whacking yourself on the head,
trying to make it go away
because it can be so lonely.
Nobody knows what I'm going through,
no one can see what I see.
I'm trying to explain it to people.
You don't know if they're gonna think you're crazy
or they're gonna empathise,
or they're gonna,
you just don't know how they're gonna react.
MILES: I'm sitting in the garden with NUSHKA,
my German Shepherd guide dog.
[ BIRDS CHIRPING; DOG WHINING ]
How do you tell someone?
I don't know, I really don't know.
It was just something that I lived with,
it was just there. I told a friend of mine
about them probably when I was about
seven, six, seven, something like that.
Not "Oh, I see these monsters," it was just, there are
these monsters, and I suspect at that age he probably
[ BIRDS CHIRPING ]
took it as a game.
But also I think he probably
knew to a point there was something
because he would ask, he'd say
"What monsters are there today?
Which ones are they? Let's get them!"
[ BIRDS CHIRPING; DOG WHINING ]
And we'd charge down the corridor, we'd attack these things,
and it actually felt quite good,
just to actually be on the front foot,
[ EXHALES ], felt good.
[ WATER FLOWING ]
NINA: Reflections of images through water.
[ ♪ MELANCHOLIC MUSIC ♪ ]
From the moment I was told the that it was just my mind,
and I saw those wavy colours,
it was probably about five or six weeks that I kept it to myself,
which is, doesn't seem
that long but for me, it felt like months
and it got to the point where I just, like,
I can't do this alone anymore.
I have to speak to somebody
but I was really scared of telling anyone,
because I thought,
“They're going to think I'm going mad."
"What you mean you can see someone
in the corner of the room?"
"What do you mean you can see
a crocodile crawling across the living room?”
“Are you going crazy? You're mental?”
They're gonna think that I'm having a nervous breakdown,
because I've lost my sight, and I've lost my business
and I've lost, you know, stick me on a load of tablets,
and I'm just going to become a vegetable in the
corner of the room. So, I was really scared to tell
anyone, so I told my mom and husband
and they didn't have a clue, but they were
really understanding and patient and
"Right let's try and find out what's going on."
And that's when I came across
Judith Potts and Esme's Umbrella.
[ BIRDS CHIRPING ] So, I emailed her
and explained what I was going through
and she replied and said
"Yeah, you've got Charles Bonet syndrome."
And I was like "Wooh, what's that?"
It just felt amazing that she's told me that I have this condition.
It's got a name.
Wow, even though I had no idea what it was,
I had something that had a name,
and a partial explanation.
[ ♪ ORCHESTRAL MUSIC ♪ ]
MILES: Back in the doll's house, a documentary is playing on TV.
We hear from Judith Potts, Professor Mariya Moosajee,
and Professor Dominic Ffytche.
JUDITH POTTS: When you full sight, there are messages
which run all the time from the retina
in the eye to the visual cortex in the brain.
The eye acting like a camera
and the brain interpreting what it is you're seeing.
When sight diminishes, those messages slow down
or stop entirely.
But the brain doesn't. The brain doesn't kind of retire
at that point, the brain, with nothing to interpret
fires up, and creates its own images,
which are the visual hallucinations.
MARIYA MOOSAJEE: These are purely visual hallucinations,
and they're not linked to any kind of mental illness.
Charles Bonet syndrome is a side
effect of losing one's vision,
and it manifests as visual hallucinations.
If you could imagine, if you're looking at your surroundings
and part of your eye isn't working properly,
and it can't see very well,
it could be like a jigsaw.
There are parts of the jigsaw with the pieces there
and then there are dark bits,
where the pieces aren't present.
Your brain realises that there are gaps in
your vision, and it tries to fill
those gaps with an image.
DOMINIC FFYTCHE: So Charles Bon syndrome ranges from
very simple types of hallucination, it could be just a
colour blob or a line, to about 60%
of people who will describe a disembodied face,
and it's often distorted in some way
and so, people will describe it like a monster or
a gargoyle or grotesque in some way.
And then we get into sort of the rarer types.
About a third of people will see actual text or a sentence written there
but when you try to read it, it doesn't make sense,
and there's a variant to that with musical notation.
We don't know what's special about that type of
object but that seems to be a typical
Charles Bonnet syndrome hallucination.
NINA: Waves of yellow.
A white bird moving in the corner.
[ ♪ SOFT ELECTRONIC MUSIC ♪ ]
So, they're here right now with me
[ WATER FLOWING ]
I've got kind of yellow clouds, and it's a kind of like
[ SEAGULLS SQUAWKING ]
white little bird floating here at the side,
and clouds are moving just gracefully.
Yeah, I can't shift them.
Yesterday, I had a bit of a meltdown with my technology,
and it wasn't doing what I needed it to do
and I was getting really stressed out with it.
In that moment, that's when the zombie
faces started appearing as well.
Sometimes they've made me fall down
the stairs or walk into doors
because all of a sudden a tiger might just pop up
in front of me, and it kind of takes me off guard.
[ BIRDS CHIRPING; DOG WHINING ]
MILES: You just don't know, you don't think about it being a "thing”.
Being a recognised syndrome,
which I think has made things a lot easier.
I think it's my experience that in the eight months
since I’ve actually started talking about them,
I don’t think they’re as intrusive, not as agressive.
They’re still always there
and they still do have their times,
[ BIRDS CHIRPING ]
but the times are currently less frequent,
so maybe I won't say talking about them
has cured them at all, because like I said,
they're still there every time,
just all the time, they are there.
But maybe it has, in some way,
enabled me not to be so worried about them
NINA: Shimmering animations of hallucinations
play behind silhouettes of Miles and myself.
[ ♪ PERCUSSION AND JAZZ MUSIC BUILDS ♪ ]
To my Charles Bonet syndrome, I would just like to say “Welcome”.
Our journey has been a turbulent one
and I was unsure of which way it would go.
I can now safely say you're a part of me,
and I welcome all of you.
MILES: Dear monsters of Charles Bonnet syndrome.
Since I was five, you have intruded into
my life without so much as a by-your-leave.
When I was 4 and a half and lost my sight
you lost not a second stepping into the void.
In those days, you terrorised me with many forms.
NINA: When you first came into my life,
you were a stranger, unknown.
You appeared in a flourish of colour and a subtle wave.
You were barely even there, but as you grew,
so did my fear and loneliness.
MILES: The number of your forms decreased over the years.
But none of you lost a moment or an
opportunity to try and intimidate me
and insinuate yourselves into my life.
I finally found out what you are
and in the eight months since then,
I've begun to be able to do the hardest thing
and tell people about you.
[ ♪ SNARE DRUMMING STOPS ♪ ]
NINA: Then, that moment came in a second,
when, sat there alone, that I am in control.
[ ♪ SOFT SYNTH MUSIC STARTS ♪ ]
I began to share and tell people more of you.
And as I did, you became a part of me.
I learned about you.
I found out who you were and why you existed.
[ ♪ PERCUSSION MUSIC BUILDS ♪ ]
Do you have any idea how hard it is
to tell those that you love, that you have been
terrified out of your wits all your life
and haven't been able to tell them.
You bully and intimidate and like bullies the world over.
Once you are exposed yourselves,
you weaken, you diminish.
NINA: A breath, a moment, a thought,
and I am in control again.
There are the times we get along,
and this is where you show your fun side
with bubbles, stars, and plenty of colour.
I own you. I'm going to tell as many people
about you as I can
in the hope that less people have to spend their
lives trapped inside their own heads with you.
I want to take what I've learnt from my life with you
in the hope that it will teach others and help them.
MILES: In short, your days are numbered.
You will be understood
and with understanding
comes acceptance and ownership
and with acceptance and ownership comes freedom.
[ ♪ MUSIC STOPS ♪ ]
NINA: On that note, Charles Bonnet syndrome, I thank you.
I am not so scared anymore.
NARRATOR: One in fve people with sight loss experience some degree of Charles Bonnet syndrome.
With as many as 1 million in the UK alone.
[ ♪ PERCUSSION MUSIC ♪ ]
[ ♪ PERCUSSION MUSIC FADES ♪ ]