[ HEARTBEAT ]
NINA: Abstract image of an eye.
[ ♪ PERCUSSION AND SYNTH STARTS ♪ ]
Am I crazy? Am I blind?
Should I be hard
or should I be kind
as I stand and shake my head?
For no one knows what I see,
yet I am always there to please.
Colours wash over the screen.
[ ♪ MUSIC RISES ♪ ]
MILES: They're not real,
or they're more real,
should I say than,
maybe a sighted person can imagine.
You probably do without realising,
but you can feel when things are there,
even if you're not touching them.
You learn,
as someone who can't see at all,
to rely on that feeling.
It, you know,
it saves you.
And these hallucinations are so,
so real,
[ ♪ MUSIC CLIMAXES ♪ ]
yes, you can see them,
but you also...
feel them.
[ ♪ MUSIC STOPS SUDDENLY AND FADES ♪ ]
NARRATOR: Aspectum
MILES: I'm Miles.
I'm at the empty cricket stadium.
[ DISTANT SHOUTING ]
Started playing County
and then started playing
International England cricket
from '98 through 2008.
[ BALL THUDDING ]
It's a lot of really good fun.
It was...
Got to see places around the world
that I wouldn't have been able to see
had I been able to see.
Through just playing cricket,
the sport that I've loved since I was
[ LAWN MOVER ]
as far back as I can remember.
My dad, when I was five years old,
sat on the sofa with him
explaining fielding positions.
When I was 18 months old,
my mom noticed that the pupil in my right eye
wasn't working properly
when she turned the lights on and off,
and took me off down to the doctors.
[ CRACKLING NOISE ]
Then went straight down there
and was diagnosed with Retina Blastoma,
so it's a cancer of the retina.
[ NOISE BUILDING ]
It was in both eyes,
but it was much further progressed
in my right eye.
So far so
they had to remove that eye instantly,
and straight away.
They reckoned that five weeks later,
the cancer would have been into the optic nerve
and the brain
and that would have been it.
And that would be the end of stuff.
[ STADIUM AMBIENCE AND SINE WAVE ]
I did radiotherapy on my left eye
for the next three years.
Cobalt plaques on the back of the eyeball
and all that sort of stuff
to try and fry the cancer.
But in the end,
it didn't work.
It was too resilient.
So they took my left eye
when I was four and a half.
[ CRACKLING NOISE STARTS ]
NINA: I'm Nina.
I developed a sight condition
when I was two years old.
I caught the flu virus
and it attacked my eyes.
It left me with different problems.
I lost my right eye 13 years ago
in an accident at work.
[ CLINKING ]
And then I lost the retina out of the left eye
coming up to four years ago now
in an accident at home.
[ DEEP DRONE ]
That morning I was taking too much on,
[ KETTLE WHISTLING ]
doing the payroll for the staff at the cafe,
I was trying to get my son ready for school.
I bent over,
basically caught the corner of the TV
and it burst a hole in the top of my eyeball.
And I knew straight away
the site just, it went just black.
There was just like lines of lightning.
[ DRONE SWELLING ]
And I just knew. I knew that the site had gone.
It was quite frightening.
I came around from surgery
and I just saw waves of blue and red
and I thought,
"They've saved something that I can see,
"I can see something
they've saved some of my sight."
Doctor came back
and I remember these words,
he said: "I can reassure you
we haven't saved your sight,
"it's just your mind playing tricks on you."
So those words kind of haunted me
because I thought,
"Well, I can see something,
there's something there for sure."
[ SINE WAVES FADE IN ]
Because he said that to me
I was really scared to tell anybody.
[ FLOWING WATER ]
Waves of blue, yellow, and green wash over the screen.
The images started to develop from that point,
and I started seeing patterns
and shapes and the colours,
the blue and red turned into
green and yellow and pink,
and purple,
and then they started forming shapes,
and then they became faces
and the faces were
kind of turned into like a skull,
a zombie skull
and they had no eyes in the sockets
and they had blood dripping down the cheeks.
[ DISSONANT SOUNDS ]
It just become too scary.
I was just sat there crying,
kind of huddled on the sofa in the corner
just scared of these zombies that were there.
Here's some artwork I made of the skulls.
MILES: We enter a doll's house recreation
of my childhood home.
[ ♪ EERIE PIANO
AND REVERSED SOUNDS STARTS ♪ ]
So I first started getting hallucinations
when I was probably about four.
I think it was just before
I totally lost my sight.
Mine have always been
what I've always called "monsters".
Ones that were good,
ones that were friendly,
[ STAIRS CREAK ]
ones that weren't.
So I guess the friendly ones,
they just sort of sat back.
They were never a threat.
[ WHOOSHES ]
There were two in particular I remember
when I was young,
and they were sort of snakes,
[ HISSES ]
and they were not friendly.
They... were as thick as your arm,
and they had kind of thick, wormy hair.
When you're a child,
and your parents have gone out,
and your grandparents
are sitting for the evening,
and you've gone to bed,
sometimes, you know, as a child,
you'd wake up and go:
"Oh, I want me mum, I want me dad!"
or whatever.
I couldn't go to the door to call downstairs
to my gran or my granddad or whatever
because as soon as I opened the door a crack...
[ STEPS CREAK ]
[ DRUMS START ]
one or both of these snakes would be outside
and they'd try and come through the door.
So you might whip it open, shout, slam it,
and dive back into bed again...
but you probably wouldn't.
So you either just shouted a lot from there
or you bottled everything up
and got under the duvet
where you couldn't see,
metaphorically speaking.
Because that works for me.
If I'm seeing a monster,
if I cover my eyes, I can't see it.
Work that one out.
NINA: I walk through a mirror maze with my cane,
reflections of myself appearing and disappearing.
It does have an impact
and I know some days I feel like,
[ PERCUSSIONS ]
"God, I just can't carry on. I'm just this...
I can't cope with this anymore,
I need to shut, I need to close,
I need to go away,
I need to get away, I need to escape it
and I can't escape it,
it's there and I have
them bad days.
So for me,
I experience them all day, every day.
So from the moment I waked,
to the moment I get to sleep
or when I get to sleep
because that is one thing that I struggle with,
getting to sleep
because when the hallucinations are there,
they're there when I close my eyes,
they don't go away.
It drives me insane sometimes(!)
I just, like... I know it sounds,
and I probably shouldn't say this in front of everyone
but it sounds like some days,
and especially it's more at nighttime
when I'm trying to get to sleep, but...
I smack myself on the head.
I shake.
You know, I lie there in bed crying,
begging for it to go away
because I just want to go to sleep.
And that is really difficult to live with.
And when you can't make it go away,
that's hard.
And then you know, and then you feel,
then you get guilt and shame
for whacking yourself on the head
to try and make it go away.
Because it can be so lonely.
You know,
nobody knows what I'm going through,
no one can see what I see.
I'm trying to explain it to people.
You don't know if they're going to think
you're crazy,
or they're gonna empathise,
or they're gonna...
You just don't know how they're going to react.
MILES: I'm sitting in the garden with NUSHKA,
my German Shepherd guide dog.
[ BIRDS CHIRPING; DOG WHINING ]
How do you tell someone?
I don't know, I really don't know.
It was just something that I lived with,
it was just there. I told a friend of mine
about them probably when I was about
seven, six, seven, something like that.
Not “Oh, I see these monsters”,
it was just: “There are these monsters”.
And I suspect at that age he probably
[ BIRDS CHIRPING ]
took it as a game.
But also I think he probably
knew to a point there was something.
Because he would ask, he'd say
"What monsters are there today?
Which ones are they? Let's get them!"
[ BIRDS CHIRPING; DOG WHINING ]
And we'd charge down the corridor,
we’d-we’d attack these things,
a-and it actually felt quite good,
just to actually be on the front foot,
felt…
[ EXHALES ]
felt good.
[ DOG WHINING ]
[ WATER FLOWING ]
NINA: Reflections of images through water.
[ ♪ MELANCHOLIC SYNTHS ♪ ]
From the moment I was told
that it was just my mind,
and I saw those wavy colours,
it was probably about five
or six weeks that I kept it to myself,
which is, doesn't seem
that long but for me, it felt like months
and it got to the point where I just,
like, I can't do this alone anymore.
I have to speak to somebody
but I was really scared of telling anyone,
because I thought,
“They're going to think I'm going mad."
"What you mean you can see someone
in the corner of the room?
"What do you mean you can see a crocodile
crawling across the living room?
“Are you going crazy? You're mental?”
They're gonna think
that I'm having a nervous breakdown,
because I've lost my sight,
and I've lost my business
and I've lost, you know…
stick me on a load of tablets,
and I'm just going to become a vegetable in the
corner of the room. So, I was really scared
to tell anyone. So I told my mom and husband
and they didn't have a clue, but they were
really understanding and patient and
"Right let's try
and find out what's going on."
And that's when I came across
Judith Potts and Esme's Umbrella.
[ BIRDS CHIRPING ]
So, I emailed her
and explained what I was going through
and she replied and said
"Yeah, you've got Charles Bonnet syndrome."
And I was like "Wooh, what's that?"
It just felt amazing that
she's told me that I have this condition.
It's got a name. Wow!
Even though I had no idea what it was,
I had something that had a name,
and a partial explanation.
[ ♪ ORCHESTRAL MUSIC ♪ ]
MILES: Back in the doll's house,
a documentary is playing on TV.
We hear from Judith Potts, Prof
Mariya Moosajee, and Prof Dominic Ffytche.
JUDITH: When you full sight, there
are messages which run all the time
from the retina in the eye
to the visual cortex in the brain.
The eye acting like a camera and the brain
interpreting what it is you're seeing.
When sight diminishes,
those messages slow down
or stop entirely.
But the brain doesn't.
The brain doesn't kind of retire at that
point, the brain, with nothing to interpret
fires up, and creates its own images,
which are the visual hallucinations.
MARIYA: These are
purely visual hallucinations.
and they're not linked
to any kind of mental illness.
Charles Bonnet syndrome is a side effect
of losing one's vision, and
it manifests as visual hallucinations.
If you could imagine,
if you're looking at your surroundings
and part of your eye isn't working
properly, and it can't see very well,
it could be like a jigsaw. There are
parts of the jigsaw with the pieces there
and then there are dark bits,
where the pieces aren't present.
Your brain realises
that there are gaps in
your vision, and it tries to fill
those gaps with an image.
DOMINIC:
So Charles Bonnet syndrome ranges from
very simple types of hallucination.
It could be just a colour blob
or a line, to about 60% of people
who will describe a disembodied face,
and it's often distorted in some way
and so, people will describe it like a monster or
a gargoyle or grotesque in some way.
And then we get into sort of the rarer types.
About a third of people will see
actual text or a sentence written there
but when you try to read it,
it doesn't make sense,
and there's a variant
to that with musical notation.
We don't know what's special
about that type of object
but that seems to be a typical
Charles Bonnet syndrome hallucination.
NINA: Waves of yellow.
A white bird moving in the corner.
[ ♪ SOFT SYNTH ♪ ]
So, they're here right now with me
[ WATER FLOWING ]
I've got kind of yellow clouds,
and it's a kind of like
[ SEAGULLS SQUAWKING ]
white little bird floating here at the side,
and clouds are moving just gracefully.
Yeah, I can't shift them.
Yesterday, I had
a bit of a meltdown with my technology,
and it wasn't doing what I needed it to do
and I was getting really
stressed out with it.
In that moment,
that's when the zombie faces
started appearing as well.
Sometimes they've made me fall down
the stairs or walk into doors
because all of a sudden
a tiger might just pop up in front of me,
and it kind of takes me off guard.
[ BIRDS CHIRPING; DOG WHINING ]
MILES: You just don't know it’s a…
You don't think about
it being a… being a "thing”.
Being a recognised syndrome,
which, which I think
has made things a lot easier.
I think it's my experience that
in the eight months
since I’ve actually started talking about them,
I don’t think they’re as intrusive,
not as aggressive.
They’re still always there
and they still do have their times,
[ BIRDS CHIRPING ]
but the times are currently less frequent,
so maybe,
I won't say talking about them
has cured them at all,
because like I said,
they're still there every time,
just all the time, they are there.
But maybe it has, in some way,
enabled me not to be so worried about them.
NINA: Shimmering animations of hallucinations
play behind silhouettes of Miles and myself.
[ ♪ PERCUSSIONS AND SYNTHS ♪ ]
To my Charles Bonnet syndrome,
I would just like to say
“Welcome”.
Our journey has been a turbulent one
and I was unsure of which way it would go.
I can now safely say you're a part of me,
and I welcome all of you.
MILES: Dear monsters of Charles Bonnet syndrome.
Since I was five, you have intruded into
my life without so much as a by-your-leave.
When I was 4 and a half
and lost my sight
you lost not a second
stepping into the void.
In those days,
you terrorised me with many forms.
NINA: When you first came into my life,
you were a stranger, unknown.
You appeared in a flourish
of colour and a subtle wave.
You were barely even there,
but as you grew,
so did my fear and loneliness.
MILES: The number of your forms
decreased over the years.
But none of you lost a moment or an
opportunity to try and intimidate me
and insinuate yourselves into my life.
I finally found out what you are
and in the eight months since then,
I've begun to be able to
do the hardest thing
and tell people about you.
[ ♪ SNARE DRUMMING STOPS ♪ ]
NINA: Then, that moment came in a second,
when, sat there alone, that I am in control.
[ ♪ SOFT SYNTHS ADDED ♪ ]
I began to share and tell people more of you.
And as I did,
you became a part of me.
I learned about you. I found out
who you were and why you existed.
Do you have any idea how hard it is
to tell those that you love, that you
have been terrified out of your wits
all your life
and haven't been able to tell them.
You bully and intimidate
and like bullies the world over.
Once you are exposed yourselves,
you weaken, you diminish.
NINA: A breath, a moment, a thought,
and I am in control again.
There are the times we get along,
and this is where you show your fun side
with bubbles, stars,
and plenty of colour.
I own you. I'm going to tell as many
people about you as I can in the hope
that less people have to spend their lives
trapped inside their own heads with you.
I want to take
what I've learnt from my life with you
in the hope
that it will teach others and help them.
MILES: In short,
your days are numbered.
You will be understood
and with understanding
comes acceptance and ownership
and with acceptance
and ownership comes freedom.
[ ♪ MUSIC STOPS ♪ ]
NINA: On that note, Charles Bonnet
syndrome, I thank you.
I am not so scared anymore.
NARRATOR: One in five people with sight loss
experience some degree of Charles Bonnet syndrome.
With as many as 1 million in the UK alone.
[ ♪ PERCUSSION MUSIC ♪ ]
[ ♪ PERCUSSION MUSIC FADES ♪ ]